<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An anatomy of the Lords tyranny and iniustice exercised upon Lieu. Col. Iohn Lilburne, now a prisoner in the Tower of London. Delivered in a speech by him, Novem. 6. 1646. before the honorable Committee of the House of Commons, appointed to consider of the priviledges of the commons of England: the originall copy of which, he in obedience to the order and command of the said Committee, delivered in writing to the hands of Col. Henry Martin, chairm-man of the said Committee: Nov. 9. 1646 and now published to the view of all the commons of England, for their information, &amp; knowledge of their liberties and priviledges.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2080</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E362_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201211</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861743</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113886</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88156)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113886)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 58:E362[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An anatomy of the Lords tyranny and iniustice exercised upon Lieu. Col. Iohn Lilburne, now a prisoner in the Tower of London. Delivered in a speech by him, Novem. 6. 1646. before the honorable Committee of the House of Commons, appointed to consider of the priviledges of the commons of England: the originall copy of which, he in obedience to the order and command of the said Committee, delivered in writing to the hands of Col. Henry Martin, chairm-man of the said Committee: Nov. 9. 1646 and now published to the view of all the commons of England, for their information, &amp; knowledge of their liberties and priviledges.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 13th 1646".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Civil rights --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113886:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Anatomy of the Lords Tyranny and iniuſtice exerciſed upon Lieu. Col. IOHN LILBURNE, now a priſoner in the Tower of LONDON.</head>
            <head type="sub">Delivered in a ſpeech by him, Novem. 6. 1646. before the honorable Committee of the Houſe of Commons, appointed to conſider of the priviledges of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England: The originall Copy of which, he in obedience to the order and command of the ſaid Committee, delivered in writing to the hands of Col. <hi>Henry Martin,</hi> Chairm-man of the ſaid Committe: Nov. 9. 1646 and now publiſhed to the view of all the Commons of England, for their information, &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their Liberties and Priviledges.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To the Honorable the COMMITTEE for the Liberty of the Commons of ENGLAND.</salute>
May it pleaſe this Honorable Committee, in obedience to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and Order of the <hi>6.</hi> of November laſt, I here humbly preſent you with the narration under my hand, which by word of mouth I made unto you upon Friday laſt, of my particular ſufferings ſince my commitment by the Lords.</opener>
            <p>MAY it pleaſe this Honorable Committee, I had a hearing before you upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 27, of <hi>October</hi> laſt, and then I truly acquainted you with the manner of the Lords firſt ſending for me to their Barre, by order of the 10. <hi>June,</hi> 1646. to anſwer a charge there. I acquainted you truly, what paſſed betwixt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113886:2"/>their meſſenger &amp; my ſelf, &amp; alſo what was ſaid to me at their Bar, and how that for no misbehaviour, or any other cauſe, ſaving my exhibiting to them my Proteſt, and refuſing to anſwer illegall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories: they, the 11. of <hi>June,</hi> 1646. committed mee to <hi>Newgate:</hi> and how that upon the 16. of <hi>June,</hi> 1646. I ſent my appeale to the Honorable Houſe of Commons; which was accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, And the laſt time I was before you, I was reading the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Warrant of the Lords to bring me the ſecond time to their Barre: In the midſt of which you were called away; and therefore for what then paſſed, I ſhall referre you, Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> to your own Notes, and my Papers delivered in to you; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to my printed relation of their firſt proceedings with me, which you have.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall humbly deſire liberty methodically to goe on: And as to me it appeares, the Lords taking notice that I had appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to your Houſe (their indignation being thereby increaſed;) ſent a warrant the 22. of <hi>June,</hi> 1646. to the Keeper of <hi>Newgate,</hi> in theſe words:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="warrant">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ordered by the Lords in Parliament aſſembled, that Lieutenant Colonell</hi> John Lilburne, <hi>now a priſoner in Newgate, ſhall be brought before their Lordſhips (in the high Court of Parliament) to morrow morning by</hi> 10. <hi>of the clock. And this to be a ſufficient Warrant in that behalfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Brown Cler. Parl.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And I being in bed, was by my Keeper about 10, a lcock at night, certified, that ſuch a Warrant was come to carry me in the morning to the Lords Barre: I roſe betimes and went, and ſpoke with <hi>Briſco</hi> the Clerk of <hi>Newgate,</hi> and my Keepers Maſter, and told him, the Lords had no power nor juriſdiction over me by law: and therefore I told him, I neither could nor would give my conſent to goe up to them. And then he told me, he would force me. Wherupon I went up to my chamber, and locked my door, and writ a Letter to Mr. <hi>Wollaſtone,</hi> the chiefe Keeper under the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes of <hi>London:</hi> And in his abſence, my wife and a friend carried it to the Sheriffes, then at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> with the Court of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and delivered it and my appeale, &amp;c. to them; who, as they conceive, amongſt themſelves, read it. But for any thing I know,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113886:2"/>ordered <hi>Briſco</hi> to make a forcible entry upon my lodging: for hee came up, and broke my Chamber-wall, and by force carried me down, and put me in a Coach, which carried me to the Lords. The Copy of the above-mentioned letter in print, I here preſent unto you.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> This morning have ſeen a Warrant from the Houſe of Lords, made yeſterday, to command you to bring me this day at ten a clock before them: the warrant expreſſeth no cauſe wherefore I ſhould dance attendance before them; neither doe I know any ground or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherefore I ſhould, nor any Law that compels me thereunto: For their Lordſhips, ſitting by vertue of Prerogative-patents, and not by election, or common conſent of the people; have (as <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other good lawes of the land tell me,) nothing to doe to try me, or any Commoner whatſoever, in any criminall caſe, either for life, limb, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, or eſtate: But, contrary hereunto, as incroachers and uſurpers upon my freedomes and liberties; they lately and illegally endeavoured to try me a Commoner at their Bar: for which <hi>I</hi> under my hand and ſeal proteſted to their faces againſt them, as violent and illegall incroa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers upon the rights and liberties of me, and all the Commons of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, (a copy of which, &amp;c. I in print herewith, ſend you:) and at their Bar <hi>I</hi> openly appealed to my competent, proper, legall Tryers and Judges, the Commons of England aſſembled in Parliament, (for which their Lordſhips did illegally, arbitrarily, and tyrannically com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to priſon into your cuſtody,) unto whom divers dayes agoe I ſent my appeal, &amp;c. which now remains in the hands of their Speaker, if it be not already read in the Houſe, unto which I do, and will ſtand, and obey their commands.</p>
                  <p>Sir, I am a free-man of England, and therefore I am not to be uſed as a Slave, or Vaſſall, by the Lords, which they have already done, and would further doe. I alſo am a man of peace and quietneſſe, and deſire not to moleſt any, if I be not forced thereunto: therefore I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you, as you tender my good, and your own; take this for anſwer, that I cannot, without turning traytor to my Liberties, dance at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance to their Lordſhips Barre: being bound in conſcience, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to God, my ſelfe, mine, and my Countrey; to oppoſe their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments to the death: which by the ſtrength of God I am reſolved to doe.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113886:3"/>
                  <p>Sir, you may, or cauſe to be exerciſed upon me, ſome force or vie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to pull and dragge me out of my Chamber, which I am reſolved to maintain, as long as I can, before <hi>I</hi> will be compelled to goe before them: and therefore <hi>I</hi> deſire you, in a friendly way, to bee wiſe and conſiderate before you doe that, which it may be, you can never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my Cock-loft in the Preſſe-yard of</hi> Newgate <date>
                           <hi>this 13 of Iune, 1646.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                     <signed>I am your true and faire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioned priſoner, if you will be ſo to me. JOHN LILBURN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And being in the <hi>Painted Chamber</hi> talking with Col. <hi>Francis Ruſſel,</hi> a Member of your Houſe; <hi>Briſco</hi> came to me, and before him told me, that the Lords had commanded, that I ſhould not ſpeak with any. To which I replied, Are the Lords aſhamed of their cauſe, that they dare not venture my declaring of it to my friend? But, goe tell their Lordſhips from me, I underſtand the liberties of <hi>England</hi> better then ſo ſuddenly to be their ſlave, and to obey their unjuſt and tyrannicall commands: And therefore tell them, I will whether they will or no, talk with any man that will talk with me, till they out-ſtrip the Biſhops (who gagged me for ſpeaking) in cruelty, by cutting out my tongue, or ſowing up my lips.</p>
            <p>And by and by I was called into their Houſe: and being by them commanded to kneele at their Barre; I abſolutely refuſed to doe it, unleſſe they would by force compell me thereunto: which, if they did, I told them, it would bee no act of mine. And I ſhall (with your favour) give you one reaſon, which with ſome others, that made me I did not kneele; and it was this: I knew, by Law the Lords had no juriſdiction over me, and accordingly I had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed my duty to my ſelfe, &amp;c. in proteſting againſt them, and had appealed to your Houſe, as the abſolute legall ſupreame power of the Kingdome, and ſo) farre and by many degrees above the Lords. Now if I ſhould have done any action that ſhould have declared any ſubjection unto the power and judicature of the Lords (which my kneeling would have done,) I had not onely turned traytor there by, to the Lawes and Liberties of <hi>England;</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113886:3"/>but I had alſo undone all that before I had done, and deprived my ſelfe both of the benefit of my Proteſt and Appeale, and ſhould alſo by my own act, have laid my ſelfe open, juſtly to be ſentenced, and puniſhed by the Lords.</p>
            <p>And upon refuſall to kneele, they commanded me to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and made this Order. </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="warrant">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Die Martis</hi> 23. <hi>Junii</hi> 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ORdered by the Lords aſſembled in Parliament, that <hi>Iohn Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne</hi> ſhall ſtand committed cloſe Priſoner, in the Priſon of <hi>Newgate:</hi> and that he be not permitted to have pen, inke, or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and none ſhall have acceſſe unto him in any kinde, but onely his Keeper, untill this Court doth take further order.</p>
                  <trailer>To the Keeper of Newgate his Deputy or Deputies.</trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Iohn Brown Cler: Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum. Exam. per. Rad, Briſcoe Cleric: de Newgate.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Now I ſhall humbly deſire this Honourable Committee, in the firſt place to obſerve; that the Lords Warrant of the 22. June, 1646. expreſſeth no cauſe at all wherefore I ſhould dance atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance at their Barre, and therefore illegall. 2. I alſo intreate this Honourable Committee to obſerve, that the Lords Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment of me 23. June cloſe Priſoner is altogether illegall, and againſt the Petition of Right; which is confirmed with every clauſe in it, by the act that aboliſheth the tax of Ship-money, made this preſent Parliament, and, as Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> that learned Lawyer doth well and truly obſerve in the 2. part of his inſtitutes folio. 52. there are 4. things that are required to make
<list>
                  <item>1. That he or they which do commit; have lawfull authority. a Commitment lawfull, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That their warrant or mittimus be lawfull, and that (ſaith he) muſt be in writing, under hand and Seal.</item>
                  <item>3. The cauſe muſt be contained in the warrant, as, for treaſon, fellony, &amp;c. or for ſuſpition of treaſou, felony, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>4. The warrant or mittimus containing a lawfull cauſe, ought to have a lawfull concluſion, <hi>viz.</hi> and him ſafely to keepe, untill he be delivered by law, &amp;c. and not untill the party committing doth further order. All which 4. are wanting in this warreat; and therefore altogether illegall and unjuſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now may it pleaſe this Committee; I was very free in my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113886:4"/>with Mr. <hi>Wollaſton,</hi> &amp;c. the Keeper of <hi>Newgate,</hi> about the illegallity of this warrant, which, it may be, came to the Lords eares, and therefore within 4. or 5. dayes after, they ſent a more formall warrant containing the cauſe of my commitment, and as Mr. <hi>Briſco</hi> could me, tooke the aforeſaid warrant away, the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall copyes of all which orders are in your hands Mr. <hi>Martin,</hi> and were delivered to you upon the firſt examination of this buſineſſe, about 4. moneths agoe, to which I humbly referr you.</p>
            <p>Now may it Pleaſe you to give me leave to go on with the true relation of the barbarous and tyrannicall execution of this unjuſt order, by vertue of which for about 3. weeks together, I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred of pen, inke, or paper, and my Chamber, by Mr. <hi>Briſco,</hi> for that end, ſtrictly ſearched, and my wife, councellers and friends kept from me: my wife, &amp;c. after I was firſt locked up, not being permitted to ſet her foote within my Chamber doore, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to come into the Priſon yard, to ſpeake with me out of my window, nor I ſuffered to receive from the hands of my wife, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, or friends, either meat, drinke, money, or any other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries; and yet their Lordſhips, nor none by their order, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me all that time, the valew of one penny loaf to live upon, and though my wife obtained ſo much favour from a neighbour to ſpeake with me out of their windowes, at the diſtance of about 40. or 50 yards, it being impoſſible for us to ſay any thing, but what the Jaylors if they had a minde might heare, yet ſuch was their inhuman cruelty, that they often threatned to ſtop up the poore mans windowes, if he would not ceaſe to permit my wife to look out of them, and alſo threatned me to boord up mine, or elſe if I would not forbeare, at that diſtance, to ſpeake with my wife, to lay me in <hi>Newgate</hi> Priſon, where as they could me, I ſhould nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have a poſſibility to ſpeake with her or any other, which I bid them do if they durſt, telling them that would be the onely way to get me my liberty; for I had ſome friends abrode that would then I did believe, to the purpoſe beſtir themſelves to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my life, which they would eaſily judge was then intended in good earneſt to be taken away by them, and therefore if any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe followed they might thanke themſelves, upon which they forbore executing their bitter menacies and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any further up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113886:4"/>
            <p>But I beſeech you further be pleaſed to obſerve the Lords guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſciences, and their brave juſtice, who the moſt part of this time while they keepe me (thus cloſe) (that it was abſolutely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for me to know what they intended to do with me) they had as I am informed, 4. Lawyers at worke to frame a charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. Serjeant <hi>Finch,</hi> Mr. <hi>Haile,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hearne,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Glover,</hi> and upon the 10. of July 1646. and not before, Mr. Serjeant <hi>Nathaniel Finch,</hi> brought in certaine Articles, by way of charge into the Houſe of Peers againſt me; which you Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> have in your hand, and therefore I humbly deſire they may be read; which was done.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, before you read the ſentence, I humbly intreat this Honourable Committee to give me leave to make ſome obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the charge, the firſt of which, that I intreate you to take notice of is, that betwixt the day of my being firſt ſummoned to anſwer a charge at the Lords barre, and the day that it was firſt brought in, or filed upon record there againſt me, is above 29. dayes, I being ſummoned the 10. of Iune 1646. and the Charge not brought in till the 10. of Iuly 1646, which is a moſt illegall and unjuſt thing in any Court whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I beſeech you obſerve that almoſt all, and the principall things layd to my charge, are pretended crimes committed, not before my being brought to their barre to anſwer a Charge, but afterwards, namely in the time of an unjuſt and provokeing impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment: and therefore a great injuſtice it is, as any can be in the world, to force a man to dance attendance at their Barre, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer a Charge, before they have filed one againſt him, or have ſo much as the pretence of a crime to lay to his charge, and then ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarily and illegally to commit a man to a tyrannicall impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there by extraordinary provocations, to neceſſitate and force a man as it were, to commit ſlips and fallings, that thereby they may pick a hole in his coate, becauſe they had none before, and then fall upon him, and deſtroy him: and this, in every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler hath been the Lords dealing with me, which I humbly conceive to be the height of tyranny and injuſtice. Now Mr. <hi>Martin,</hi> I humbly intreate you to read the ſentence, for upon the 10. Iuly, there iſſued out an order to bring me up againe to their barre, the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113886:5"/>next day, to heare my Charge read: which was accordingly put in execution.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, you having read the ſentence, I ſhall humbly crave leave, firſt, to make ſome obſervations upon it, and then ſecondly, to go on methodically with the matter of fact.</p>
            <p>And firſt, I beſeech you obſerve that the 10. Iune 1646. I was ſummoned to attend their Lordſhips in their Houſe: and the 11. Iune 1646. I there appeared, and was then committed by them to <hi>Newgate:</hi> the 16. of the ſame moneth, I appealed to the Right Honourable the Houſe of Commons as my legall and proper Iudges, who accepted, read, approved, and committed my appeale to a ſpeciall Committee, and yet notwithſtanding the 22. of the ſame moneth, the Lords command the Keeper of <hi>Newgate</hi> to bring me up to their barre, and there upon the 23. day I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted cloſe priſonet to <hi>Newgate,</hi> till the 10. Iuly 1646. at which time my Charge was brought into the Lords Houſe and not before, which was a moneth after the firſt proceſſe, or warrant iſſued out for me. All which proceedings (beſides their not having any le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Iudicature at all over mee) are erroneous and illegall, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally in theſe two points.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe I was ſummoned, before any Charge was record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which proceedings are point blanke againſt the expreſſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of 9. <hi>H.</hi> 3. 29. 5. <hi>E.</hi> 3. 9. 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. 4. 28. <hi>E.</hi> 3. 3. which expreſly ſay, that none ſhall be impriſoned nor put out of his free hold, nor of his franchiſes, nor free cuſtoms, unleſſe it be by the law of the Land, which is, that none ſhall be taken by Petition or ſuggeſtion made to our Lord the King, or to his Councel, unleſſe it be by inditement or preſentment of his good and lawfull people of the ſame neighbourhood, where ſuch deeds be done; in due manner; or by proceſſe made by Writ originall at the common law, &amp;c. which Statutes are confirmed by the petition of Right, and by the Statute for aboliſhing the Star-Chamber made this preſent Parliament.</p>
            <p>And indeed, regularly, both in law and equity, the Declaration or bill ought to be filed or recorded, before any writ or proceſſe ought to iſſue againſt the defendant, or party accuſed, either in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill or criminall cauſes; and the write, warrant, or proceſſe ought to containe the matter of the declaration, bill, or petition: and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113886:5"/>this appeares cleerly in every writ (as the learned in the law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme me) ſet forth by the Regiſter, and <hi>Fitzherberts natura bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium:</hi> and that every Engliſh bill either in Chancery, Exchequer, or Star-Chamber, doth pray, that proceſſe of <hi>ſub-pena</hi> be awar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt the defendant, which proves, that proceſſe, orders or Warrants, ought not to be awarded or granted, againſt any man out of any Court of Juſtice whatever, till his charge be recorded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in the ſame Court; and ſutable to this is your own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, in your own Declarations, <hi>Booke Decl.</hi> page 38, 39, 278, 845.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I beſeech you obſerve, that all the Lords proceedings with me, after my appeale to the honourable houſe of Commons, are void in Law; becauſe, by my appeale to the proper Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is only your Houſe, the Lords are outed of their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, or <hi>conuſans</hi> of the plea, the cauſe being removed by the Appeale, their judgment was thereby determined, or at leaſt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, being but the effect of the cauſe before them, till ſuch time as the Appeal is determined; the Appeal being a ſuperſedas to the Lords further proceeding in the ſame cauſe, and they ought not to have proceeded any further at all; but to give them as much, as by any juſt colour or claime they can challenge, they ought not any further to have gone on, without the privity, licence, and direction of the honourable houſe of Commons: and therefore, all their proceedings with me, eſpecially, ſince my Appeal to your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable houſe, are <hi>coram non judice,</hi> and therefore void and erroneous. And I further conceive, under favour, that the Lords proceedings with me, after your Houſe had accepted of my Appeal, is as great an affront and indignity offered to the majeſty, honour, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your houſe (the abſolute ſupream derivative power of all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> the original and abſolute fountain of all power therein) as their proceedings are unjuſt towards me, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the lawes and liberties of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, I beſeech you obſerve, that in their Articles, the originall and chief ſuppoſed crime that they charge me with, is, for ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> a Peer, as they call him, of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Now may it pleaſe you, to take notice, that I ſay, if his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had not been guilty, &amp; told him, that it was poſſible, I might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113886:6"/>juſtly and groundedly have proved much more againſt him, then I lay to his charge in my printed Epiſtle to Judge <hi>Reeve,</hi> &amp;c. hee would never have ſhunned and avoided the known law of the Kingdome, which ſufficiently proves a remedy for him, in caſe I had ſcandalized him: as appeares by the ſtatutes of 3. <hi>E.</hi> 1, 33. 27. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. 38. E. 3. 9. 42, <hi>E.</hi> 3. 3. 2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. 5. 12. <hi>R.</hi> 2. 11 17. <hi>R.</hi> 2. 16. which expreſly command, that if any man ſcandalize any of the great men of the kingdome he ſhall be taken, and kept in cuſtody, or put in ſecurity, till he prove what he ſaith; and in caſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; then he ſhall incur the ſame pain that the other ſhould have had, if he were attainted: and that proceſſe of the law be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them without being taken and impriſoned againſt the great Charter, and other ſtatutes; but his leaving the common common and juſt road of the kingdom, that ſufficiently provides for his reparation, if innocent, argues his knowledge of his owne guilt, or elſe he would never have betaken himſelf to an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meanes (and eſpecially in ſuch a place where himſelf is chiefe Judge in his own cauſe) and there againſt me by a kind of a legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlative and unlimitted power of Judicature, which is not in them (eſpecially ſingly) neither can they (take them in the higheſt capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city that ever law eſtated them in) proceed to determine any thing out of the way of the known and eſtabliſhed lawes, by any arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or diſcretionary Rules, when there is a known law in the caſe. And I am ſure it is a received Maxime in law, <hi>That where remedy may be had by an ordinary courſe in Law; the party grieved ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have his recourſe to extraordinaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Sir, under favour, to ſpeak truly, the Parliament properly are not (nor ought not) to meddle with cauſes betwixt party &amp; party that are decideable at common-law, they being the ſupream Judicature of the Kingdome and the laſt refuge to appeale to, by the people, in caſe of injuſtice elſe-where, and ſo may properly be called Judge of Judges, rather then Judge of particular parties and cauſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My laſt obſervation upon the ſentence, that I ſhall humbly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to take notice of, is this;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That although by the</hi> 14, <hi>Chap. of Magna Charta, it is declared that a free-man ſhall not be amer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed or fined for a ſmall fault; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of the fault, and for a great fault after the greatneſſe thereof, ſaving to him his contenement or countenance, and a merchant
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113886:6"/>likewiſe ſaving to him his Merchandize. And any other villain then the Kings ſhall be likewiſe amerced, ſaving his wainage or teame, and none of the ſaid amerciaments ſhall be aſſeſſed, but by the oath of honeſt and lawfull men of the vicinage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I beſeech you obſerve, the Lords had no oath of any honeſt man what ever, againſt me, nor one word of my own confeſſion of any guiltineſſe of any crime whatſoever, but a conſtant reſolution manifeſted to maintain the lawes and liberties of the kingdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their uſurpations; for which juſt, honeſt, and legall action, and for no other, they unrighteouſly unjuſtly, and barbarouſly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced me, not ſaving to me my contenement or countenance, or leaving me ſome reaſonable proportion after their Fines, or Amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement to live upon, in the quality or condition I had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but they amerced or find me at four thouſand pounds, which is divers thouſands of pounds more then either I am worth, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was in my life.</p>
            <p>Now I beſeech this honourable Committee to obſerve, that by this ſentence, the unrighteous &amp; cruell Lords have done as much as in them lyes, every hour of time to put me into ſuch a condition; that I ſhall be liable to have all the eſtate that I have in the world taken from me, to ſatisfie this unjuſt Fine, and ſo leave nothing for me, my wife, and ſmall children, to live upon; nay, and that which is worſe then all this, the greatneſſe of the Fine is much more then I can ſatisfie; So that in caſe all that little that I have, ſhould be ſeized upon; yet there is ſuch abundance would remain behind, which would rob me of all credit whatſoever: for, who will be ſo unwiſe, as to lend a man money that is thouſands of pounds worſe then nothing which is my caſe by this Fine: But yet this is not at all; for they commit me for 7. years (the age of a man in the eye of the Law) a priſoner to the extraordinary chargeable Priſon of the Tower, where I cannot earn one penny, nor, it being no through-fare; for me to beg a penny to live upon.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, laying all theſe things together, I beſeech you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether in the intention of the Lords, I be not expoſed to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and torments, worſe then death it ſelfe: for either by their intentions, I muſt periſh by hunger and famine, or elſe be forced to eat my wife and children, or any other that I can over-come; and what is this but the height of tyranny and cruelty, and a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113886:7"/>worſe then any death in the world; for, ſaith <hi>Jerem.</hi> in his Lamentations, <hi>Better is he that dyes by the ſword, then he that dyes by famine;</hi> and he gives the reaſon; becauſe, <hi>there is a ſpeedy end of the pain of him that dyes by the ſword; but he that dyes by hunger and famine, pines away, and is in a continuall torment, alwayes dying, and wiſhing, and longing for death. And undoubtedly, Sir, this is my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, by the intention of the Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir, having with your patience, made theſe obſeruations, I humbly deſire to goe on with the matter of fact:</p>
            <p>Which is, that upon the tenth of <hi>July,</hi> when Serjeant <hi>Finch</hi> brought in my Charge into the Houſe of Peeres, they that day made an Order to command the Sheriffs of <hi>London,</hi> the next day to bring me up to their Bar, to hear my Charge: The copy of which warrant I have not, in regard the Sheriffe (contrary to law) refuſed to give it me, although I ſent to him to deſire it: and I having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly told the Jaylors of <hi>Newgate,</hi> I could not, nor would not, go up to the Lords Bar, by vertue of their own Warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, without a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible compulſion; The Sheriffes ſent about 30. or 40. of the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders upon the Hangman, when he goes to doe execution at <hi>Tiburn,</hi> to carry me up to the Lords Bar. And being in the Painted cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I deſired Mr. <hi>Briſco,</hi> one of my Keepers and Tormenters, to to goe and tell the Lords from me, that ſeeing they had the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and boldneſſe to tread the Lawes and Liberties of <hi>England</hi> under their feet, and did ſo contemne and under-value the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Honorable Houſe of Commons, to whom I had appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as yet to goe on in their illegall courſes with mee, with whom by Law they had nothing to doe; I muſt bee forced in the higheſt nature I could, to contemne and deſpiſe their proceedings; and therefore was reſolved not to come to their Bar, without a forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble compulſion, and to come in with my hat upon my head, and to ſtop my eares when they read my Charge, in deteſtation, and bearing witneſſe againſt their uſurpations and injuſtice. So away hee went: But I was compeld in; and being brought up to the Bar, I was commanded to kneele: which I abſolutely refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And then my Lord of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> (my grand adverſary, who hath for theſe two or three yeares thirſted after my blood, for no other crime but that I was faithfull and active in executing the truſt repoſed in me, for the good of the Parliament and Kingdom;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113886:7"/>he (I ſay) as ſpeaker of the Houſe of Lords, commanded the Clerk to read me my Charge; which he began to do. At which I ſtopped my eares with my fingers, till ſuch time as I perceived the Clerks lips to leave moving. Wherupon I was commanded to with-draw: and after ſome diſtance of time, I was called in again, and was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain commanded to kneele; but I told them, My Lords, you may ſave your ſelves the expence of your breath, for I ſhall not kneele without compulſion. And then my Lord of Mancheſter told me, that I by my contumacie deprived my ſelf of much benefit that I might make unto my ſelf by examining witneſſes upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> croſſe Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories, for the evading the charge. So I deſired liberty to ſpeak: which was granted, and I ſaid,</p>
            <q>
               <p>My Lords, I do much wonder at your Lordſhips proceedings with me, that you ſhould, (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the ancient and fundamentall lawes of this kingdome) ſend for me to anſwer a charge at your Bar, before you have any fil'd againſt me; and then when I come up to your Bar, preſſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to force me, contrary to law, honeſty, and juſtice, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to inquiſition-nterrogatories, and ſo to enſnare my ſelfe, when you have no crime to lay unto my charge. My Lords, what is this elſe, but to build up what but the other day you deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? For did you not here in a full Houſe, the 15. day of Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry laſt, in this very caſe, decree; adjudge, and determine, that my ſentence in the Star-chamber, and all the proceedings thereupon, ſhall forthwith be for ever totally vacuated, obliterated, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off the File in all Courts where they are yet remaining, as illegall, and moſt unjuſt, againſt the liberty of the Subject, and law of the Land, and <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and unfit to continue upon Record? &amp;c.</p> 
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>And did you not order and adjudge me, to receive of ſome of the Judges, &amp;c. of that ſentence, 2000. l. for my reparation? But my Lords, I am very ſure, that if you your ſelves, compare your proceedings againſt me, with the proceedings of the Star-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, you will find yours to be in every particular, as illegall and unjuſt, as theirs: and therfore, I much wonder, you do not bluſh at your preſent dealing with me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Beſides, my Lords, it is very ſtrange to me that the Law of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be ſo plain and perſpicuous, to tell you, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113886:8"/>you in ſuch Caſes as mine is, have no legall juriſdiction at all over me, or the meaneſt Commoner in <hi>England,</hi> and that yet notwithſtanding, you ſhould, contrary to your duty, Oathes and Covenants, uſurp &amp; chalenge a juriſdiction over us ſo. My Lords, when I was firſt at this Bar, I under my hand and Seale, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> proteſt againſt you as uſurpers &amp; incrochers, upon the Rights and Libertyes of all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> which you received &amp; read: and I alſo appealed from you, as unrighteous Judges to my Legal, and Proper Judges, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England</hi> aſſembled in Parliament, and upon the 16. of June laſt, I ſent my petition, by way of appeal to the Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe of Commons, with a copy of my Proteſt againſt you, anexed to it, which they received, read, approued of, and Committed to a ſpeciall Committee, who ſat upon it, and as I underſtand, Paſſed a vote or votes in juſtification of the Legali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of my Procedings with you, and have promiſed me Juſtice in it; now, my Lords, I here againe at your open Barr before You all, as in the ſight of and Preſence of <hi>God,</hi> proteſt againſt you againe, and all your proceedings with me, as unjuſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous and illegal: and declare unto you all, that to my ſaid Proteſt and appeale to the honorable Houſe of Commons, I will ſticke to, ſo long as I have a life and a being, And my Lords, I tel you to your faces, that by Right, they are your Judges as well as mine in this caſe: &amp; I do not doubt, but to liue to ſee the day that they will make you to knowe, whether you will or no that they are ſo, and of their Juſtice, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, I do not in the leaſt; doubt: And therefore, my Lords, ſeeing you have dealt ſo illegally and tyrannically with mee, as you have done; I now bid defiance to your power and malice, to do the worit you can.</p>
            <p>For, my Lords, are not you the men that have been principal inſtruments to engage this Kingdom in a bloudy War, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their lawes and liberties? and have nor you all often ſworn and covenanted ſo to do? But, my Lords, it ſeem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to me, you nothing at all value your oathes, nor engagements: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my Lords, if you were in jeaſt, when you did all this, and never intended, what you declared, but meerly ſet us a fighting, to unhorſe and diſmount our old Riders &amp; Tyrants, that ſo you
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113886:8"/>might get up and ride us in their ſteads: But I doe profeſſe and aſſure your Lordſhips, that I for my part was in good ſober and ſad earneſt, and never drew my ſword in theſe warres, but princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally for my liberties and freedomes, and the lawes of the land: &amp; in the field I did adventure my life freely &amp; reſolutely, like a man of valour and courage, as it is well known to ſome of your ſelves: And I now look for, and expect the enjoyment of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat for which I fought by your meanes and iuſtigation. And therefore, my Lords, I proteſt here before the God of heaven and earth, if you ſhall be ſo unworthy as to perſevere in endeavouring the deſtruction of the fundamentall Lawes and Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> as at preſent you doe; I will venture my life and heart-blood againſt you to oppoſe you, with as much zeale and courage as ever I did any of the Kings party, that you ſet us together by the eares with.</p>
            <p>And having concluded, I was commanded to heare my Charge read: But I told them, they had no judicature at all over me, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would I in the leaſt doe any thing that ſhould declare my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to their power, although I ſhould preſently be deſtroyed for my refuſall. But my Lords, ſayd I, that you may know that my conſcience doth not accuſe me of any guilt for doing any illegall or diſhonorable action againſt my countrey or the Lawes thereof, or you, or any of you that wiſheth it well; I will wave my appeal to the Houſe of Commons, if you wil ceaſe your proceedings here: and I will anſwer any of you, or all of you, according to Law, in any Court of Juſtice in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> or any other Court in <hi>England,</hi> that hath a Legall juriſdiction over me. But the Clerk was commanded to read the Charge quite through: and I ſtopped my eares till he had done. And then the Speaker asked me, what I ſaid to my Charge? I told him, I heard it not (neither indeed did,) neither had they any legall power there to exhibit, try, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge a Charge againſt me: And therefore I again appeaſed from them; telling them, I did not in the leaſt, value the worſt they could doe to me: for I would loſe my life before I would betray or part with my fundamentall liberties; either to them, or any one in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So I was commanded to with-draw: and being out above an houre, I was the third time called in, and commanded again to kneele; which I abſolutely refuſed to doe. And then I was told
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113886:9"/>by the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> what miſery and deſtruction my obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy and contemptuous carriage, had, and would bring upon me. I told him, I weighed not their malice, nor craved their favour: So he read my ſentence, which I heard: and when he had done; with a ſmiling and merry countenance, I thanked his Lordſhip for his boon: but I deſired him to take notice of it, that I valued their ſentence no more then that I had in the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> it being in every particular as illegall as that: nay more, for the <hi>Star-chamber</hi> had a legall juriſdiction over me, which their Lordſhips in their Houſe have not: ſo I was commanded to withdraw.</p>
            <p>And being by a new Warrant that day brought to the Lieutenant of the Tower of <hi>London</hi> (the Copy of which, you Mr. <hi>Martin</hi> have in your hands; it being one of the three you had from the Lieutenant the other day) my brother Major <hi>Henry Lilburn,</hi> Lieu. Col. <hi>Wetton,</hi> and my wife being with me, I told the Lieutenant of the Tower, that my ſpirit was a little refreſhed, for all my great &amp; heavy ſentence, and my commitment to ſo chargeable a priſon, as I underſtood the Tower to be, in regard I was freed from my cloſe and cruell impriſonment, and now ſhould enjoy the ſociety of my wife and friends, but he told me I was miſtaken: Why Sir, ſaid I, my Warrant doth not command you to keep me cloſe priſoner; it only injoyns you to keep me in ſafe cuſtody, and that you take care, that I neither contrive, publiſh, or ſpread any ſeditious or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellous Pamphlet againſt both, or either Houſes of Parliament. Well! ſaith he, I cannot do that, unleſſe I keep both your wife, &amp; your friends from you; aſwell you might ſay, that you cannot perform my order, unleſſe you look me up in a Dungeon, where I ſhall neither ſee light, nor enjoy candle, or fire; for it is impoſſible in a manner, to keep a man from writing, where he hath light, who by one meanes or other, will come by Pen, Ink, and Paper.</p>
            <p>And truly Sir, it was a wonder to me, to hear the Lieutenants hard and cruell interpretation of my order, and perceiving my wife to be much troubled at his words, it took a deep impreſſion upon my ſpirit, and made me go below my accuſtomed principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; in regard of that indearedneſſe of affection, that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt my wife and my ſelf, which made me ſay to him: Sir, <hi>my wife is all the earthly comfort that now in this world I have left unto me, and ſhe is that meet help, that the wiſe God of Heaven &amp; Earth,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113886:9"/>from the beginning hath inſtituted and ordained for me, frail &amp; weak man, in my pilgrimage and vally of teares here below: and Sir, if ſuch a helpe had not been requiſite for poor man; without which, he could not have had a comfortable being in his earthly being; God would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have ordained it, and commanded man to forſake Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to live with his wife, as one fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And truly Sir, I must tell you, God hath ſo knit in affection, the hearts and ſoules of me and my wife, and made us ſo willing to help to bear one anothers burdens, that I profeſſe, as in the ſight of God, I had rather you ſhould immediatly beat out my braines, then deprive me of the ſociety of my wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, for your indempnity; before theſe my friends, I will make you a faire proffer, <hi>That if you judge, that I have either faith or truth in me, I will ingage my word and promiſe unto you, that as I am a Chriſtian, a Gentleman, and a Souldier, I will neither write a line, nor read a line written; conditionally, that you, according to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and the known Lawes of this Kingdome, permit me to enjoy the ſociety of my wife, and friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the hard-hearted Lieutenant, like a man that took delight to adde ſorrow, to the afflictions of the too much afflicted, would not embrace my proffer, which I would not have broken or viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for all the gold in <hi>England;</hi> but ſtrictly gave command to my keeper, that neither my wife, nor any other friend ſhould ſpeake with me, but in his preſence and hearing; which he being here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, is able to teſtifie unto you: and then the Lieutenant went to the Lords, and prevailed with them to make an Order to bear him out, in what he had illegally and unwarrantably done, and executed upon me, of his own head, for 5 dayes: which order, you Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> have alſo in your hands: So that by the Lieutenants meanes I was divorced from my wife, till the 16. day of <hi>September</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Upon which day, the Lords of their own accord, without my deſiring of them (who was reſolved in this caſe never to ſue for a farthings-worth of courteſie) made an Order, again to marry me to my wife, as by the Copy of it in your hands will appear. And beſides all this, he ſet and ordered his Warders at the Gate, moſt illegally to take the names and places of habitations of all my friends that came to ſee mee, on ſet purpoſe, as I may juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, to affright and ſcare all away from coming to viſit me; yea,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113886:10"/>and beſids the taking of their names, ſome of his Warders did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily abuſe both me and many of thoſe that came to viſit me, &amp; denied admittance, and turned away ſcores of my friends, as I can eaſily prove: All which cruelties, and inhumanities offered to me and my friends; I may, and ſo do; ſet upon the Lieutenants own ſcore: for I often complained to him of them; and the beſt remedy I could have, was nothing but a laugh from him at it: So that truly, Gentlemen, I do profeſſe unto you, that the hard and barbarous uſage that I have had from the Lords, and their Jaylors, (in the number of which, I reckon Col. <hi>Francis Weſt,</hi> the preſent Lieutenant of the Tower, who for all his title, is no more nor no otherwiſe to me then a Jaylor) to be worſe then death it ſelfe; which I ſeriouſly profeſſe unto you, I ſhould rather embrace, then the like uſage for ſo long time again.</p>
            <p>And therefore, give me leave to ſay unto you in this particular, as I ſaid unto my Lord <hi>Heath</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> when I was arraigned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him for my life, for drawing my ſword for your defence in the kingdomes; when he preſſed me to plead unto my indictment. My Lord, ſaid I, <hi>amend thoſe things in it that are amiſſe, and give me, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the custome of the Kingdome, my right and due; and I ſhall with all readineſſe plead unto it, profeſſing unto your Lordſhip, that the cruelties that I have endured by Irons, &amp;c, in</hi> Oxford <hi>Caſtle, by the inhumane Marſhall</hi> Smith, <hi>are ſuch, &amp; ſo great, that I had rather chuſe this night to ſet my back against a wall, and be ſhot with</hi> 20. <hi>Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, then to indure the conſtant bitterneſſe of thoſe tormenting ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, that I do, and have under-gone by Marſhall</hi> Smith, <hi>ſince my captivity under him: and the ſame I do profeſſe now unto this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, I humbly beſeech, and moſt earneſtly intreat you, not to delay me in my report to your Houſe, but to do it ſpeedily for me; that ſo I may know what to truſt to, and may not by you, from whom I may juſtly ſeek Juſtice, as my right and due (and not as a boon) be delayed any longer, having bin already long enough delayed; it being almoſt five moneths ſince I firſt made my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal unto you.</p>
            <p>For truly, I muſt plainly and ingenuouſly tell you, went not the lacombes of ſtrength, and aſſiſtance from God; the more, my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition would be inſupportable, and not any longer with patience to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113886:10"/>be ſtoop't unto by me: for it cannot but be known to divers of you, that for almoſt this ten yeares together, I have never been free from the laſhes and deſtroyings of the Grand Prerogative-men of this kingdome, that have ruled and governed by no other law, then that of their own will; and yet to this day never received a penny by way of reparation, for all the wrongs and injuries that I from them have ſuſtained; although I have ſpent divers hundreds of of pounds in indeavouring the procurement of it: and my repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for my ſufferings at the hands of the <hi>Star-Chamber Judges</hi> ſticks in your houſe at this very day; which I humbly intreat this honourable Committee, when this my buſineſſe is reported to the houſe, to put them in mind of; and beſides, my late extraordinary expences, and my ſhortneſſe of pay for my faithfull and ſucceſsfull ſervice with my grand adverſary the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and the preſent extraordinary chargeableneſſe of my impriſonment in the Tower, &amp;c. renders my condition an extraordinary object of your preſent reliefe: For although I have not paid all the great ſummes demanded as fees in that place; yet becauſe I have found civility, and humanity from my Keeper, for my own accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and eaſe-ſake; I have weekly been (I think) very liberall unto him, I am ſure beyond my preſent ability; beſides the charge of my own diet and family, &amp;c. which I hope, that when your Honorable Houſe hath adjudged my cauſe, (which I am confident according to law cannot goe amiſſe with me) and thereby given me ground to preſent them with my bill of charges; they will not onely cauſe the Lords to pay it me again; but alſo ample reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for my hard and unjuſt ſufferings: without which, although you evacuate the ſentence, and ſet my perſon at liberty, I ſhall think that I ſcarce have juſtice to the half, having but meerly the ſhell without the kirnell. But if the greatneſſe of the Lords, by reaſon of the diſtractions of the preſent times, ſhal ſtick in my way as an hinderance therof; give me leave humbly to tell you, that the Commons of <hi>England</hi> are bound by you in a Proteſtation, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their liberties, and to ſtand to all thoſe that defend them; yea, and to bring thoſe that endeavour their deſtruction, to condigne puniſhment. In which regard I am reſolved by the ſtrength of God, in a juſt and legal way, with all earneſtneſſe to deſire, through City and Countrey, the joynt aſſiſtance of all in <hi>England,</hi> that are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113886:11"/>not willing to be ſlaves, to joyn with mee in a grand petition to your Houſe, for the obtaining of my juſt and honeſt deſires againſt the Lords. And truly, Sir, I muſt venture life and all that I have upon it. For can it appeare juſt to you, that the Lords ſhould cry out againſt the King, their Lord and Maſter, for injuſtice and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; yea, and draw their ſwords againſt him, and yet be more unjuſt themſelves? As to goe no further then my very caſe: for ſure <hi>I</hi> am, it was the Kings conſtant cuſtome to provide diet, lodging, and pay the fees of all thoſe he committed to the Tower: but the Lords for no cauſe in law at all, have committed me thither, and put me upon it, to pay all the vaſt extravagancies there for fees, &amp;c. yea, and that for tormenting and deſtroying me. Surely, Sir, they will never be ſo unjuſt, but when they know, it is demanded as a juſt and legall right; but largely in good currant coyn to repay me: the which, if they be ſo unjuſt as to refuſe, <hi>I</hi> hope you will be ſo juſt and true to your truſt, according to that ſufficient power and authority that is in you to compell them.</p>
            <p>And, Sir, <hi>I</hi> humbly crave reparations from all their inſtruments, that with, and upon, me have out-ſtript the bounds of the Law, in executing their meere malicious wills upon me. And, under fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, <hi>I</hi> am very confident, the Lieutenant of the Tower will bee found guilty in this particular; which <hi>I</hi> have the more ground to preſſe upon him, then the Jaylors of <hi>Newgate:</hi> For, to bee hardly and inhumanly dealt withall from ſuch bloody men as they are commonly reported to be, is no wonder; but to receive the like meaſure, nay and worſe, from the hands of Col. <hi>Francis Weſt,</hi> my fellow-citizen, (who out-ſtript his orders) a man who hath been in the field with his ſword in his hand, pretending to adventure his life for the preſervation of the lawes and liberties of <hi>England;</hi> is that that amazeth me, that he ſhould ſo farre forget himſelfe, as ſo furiouſly to fall upon me, to torment, undoe, and deſtroy me, for no other cauſe, but for being true to my principles, and the generall and publick intereſt of the Kingdome, in ſtanding for the Lawes and Liberties thereof, againſt thoſe that would deſtroy them; and which action renders him to me, to be one of the unworthieſt of the ſonnes of men; eſpecially of thoſe that would bee reputed to have the principles of an honeſt man in him.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113886:11"/>
            <p>Now Sir, to conclude all, having ſufficiently intrenched upon your patience; <hi>I</hi> make my moſt humble ſute unto this honourable Committee, That when you make my Report unto the houſe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as you tell me, you are principally to report matter of Fact, &amp; not matter of law, in point of the Lords Juriſdiction; by means of which, it may be, in your houſe many Objections may be raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, for my carriage and expreſſions before the Lords: I therefore humbly intreat you to acquaint the houſe, That it is my moſt humble deſire unto them, that ſeeing this buſineſſe is of ſo great concernment, not only to me, but alſo to your ſelves, yea, and to the whole Kingdome; that I may have that honour and juſtice, to be called to their Bar, and there have a faire, open, and publique hearing, according to Law and Juſtice; and I doubt not, but by my ſelf ſingly, by law and unqueſtionable authority, againſt all the Procters the Lords can fee in <hi>England,</hi> to plead for them; to make it cleer as the Sun that ſhines at Noon-day; that the Lords have no juriſdiction at all over me, in the caſe now in controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, and that my carriage and expreſſions before them, was, but the cordiall demonſtrations of a ſound and ſingle-harted man, who knowes himſelf bound in duty and conſcience, to God, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his country, to the utmoſt of my endeavours, to defend, and maintain his Rights and Liberties, which is as juſtifiable by the Law of this Kingdome, and in the eyes of all underſtanding men; as for a true and juſt man, to draw his ſword, and to cut a Theefe or Rogue that ſets upon him upon the high-way, on purpoſe to rob him of his life and goods.</p>
            <p>And if after ſuch a hearing before your honourable houſe, it ſhall appear to their judgments and underſtandings, that I have wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lords in generall, or the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> or Col. <hi>King</hi> in particular; (which two are the principall cauſes of all my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent trouble, and againſt whom, are two Grand charges in your houſe; as I judge them of no leſſe then high treaſon commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the Kingdom; which as I humbly conceive, the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Kingdom requires ſhould come to a finall determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) I ſhall with all willingneſſe and cheerfulneſſe ſubmit to what puniſhment ſhall be juſt for them to inflict upon me; and I hope that by this faire offer, you will be provoked with the ſtrength of reſolution, to deal impartially betwixt the Lords and me, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113886:12"/>fear, puniſh thoſe where the juſt fault is, eſpecially, conſidering that you, in your moſt excellent Declaration, of the 17. <hi>April</hi> 1646 publiſhed by you to the view of the whole kingdome, have ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly declared, <hi>That you will preſerve the Rights and Liberties of the people, and aboliſh the exerciſe of arbitrary power, and ſo provide for the ſafety and weal of the people;</hi> which is (as you ſay) <hi>the end of the primitive inſtitution of all government.</hi> And therefore, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of my ſelf, and all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> I moſt humbly beſeech, and entreat his thonourable Committee, to improve all the intereſt you have in the houſe of Commons, to make good unto us this their own juſt and honeſt Declaration.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you heare me but one word more, which I intreat you well to obſerve; that the Lords have joyned with you in ſeverall Declarations; in which the Kings Oath is printed, which I read in the Book Decl. pag. 268.713.714, where you and they declare poſitively, and back it with many ſtrong arguments; That the King by his Coronation-Oath, is bound to paſſe ſuch lawes, as his people ſhall chuſe: and if ſo; then he hath no power in him to give a law unto the people, or impoſe a law upon them: much leſſe can hee give a power to the Lords (his meer creatures made by his will &amp; pleaſure) for them to oppoſe or give a Law unto the people: and I am ſure, if they have a legiſlative power in them, to do what they pleaſe, and ſo by the authority of that, preſumed to do with mee, as they did: I am ſure, by the eſtabliſhed Law of the Kingdom, they have no power at all, not in the leaſt to do with me as they have done.</p>
            <p>And therefore, I humbly entreat you, to preſſe home unto your Houſe, the Lords uſurpations and incroachments upon our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon rights, that ſo they may effectually curbe them, as in Juſtice they ought. For Sir, that which addes ſorrow to all my ſorrowes, is this, that I ſuffer all theſe inhumanities and illegall uſages, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of the ſitting of a free Parliament, (and yet can have no effectuall redreſſe in five moneths time, though earneſtly ſought for.) Alas Sir, the Parliament is the Engliſh-mans legall laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge; and if that faile us (to ſpeak as men) we are undone; unleſſe God ſet his power at work, to work miracles, and raiſe up meanes for our preſervation. And Sir, if the Lords dare thus tyrannize over the free Commons of <hi>England</hi> in time of Parliament, (that uſed to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113886:12"/>be the fear and dread of Offendors) what is it, that they will not do unto us out of a Parliament? Therefore, again I moſt earneſtly beſeech this honourable Committee, to remember them, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove all your intereſt to puniſh, or at leaſt effectually to curbe them: for which, as well, as for your preſent patience, in hearing me ſo largely, I ſhall both now (as well as formerly) remain oblie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to improve my beſt and utmoſt ability, for the preſervation of the juſt, ſupreame intereſt, power, and authority of your honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſa. 48.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Behold, I have refined thee, but not with ſilver; I have choſen thee in the fulneſſe of affliction.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job. 23.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When he hath tryed me, I ſhall come forth as gold.</p>
            </q>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Novemb. the 9. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>JOHN LILBURN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Reader, thou art requeſted to take notice of two faults committed in the printing of this Booke, the firſt, in page <hi>2.</hi> line <hi>1.</hi> left out <hi>[and alſo what paſſed betwixt my L.</hi> Wharton <hi>and my ſelf]</hi> the <hi>2.</hi> in. p. <hi>5.</hi> l. <hi>26.</hi> where thou ſhalt find theſe words [<hi>a Commitment lawful,</hi> viz.] to be in the <hi>28.</hi> line, which ought to be placed at the end of the <hi>26.</hi> line, as thou mayſt eaſily perceive. For other faults (if thou meet with any) impute them not unto the Authour, who could not be at the correcting hereof; but in love to him, amend them.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
